THABISO MOTSWAGOLE

Senior Full Stack Developer

🕒 +26774513827 @ tsmotswagole@outlook.com 🔗 http://localhost:3000/react-portfolio 🗸 Gaborone, Botswana

SUMMARY

A talented software developer with 5+ years experience in building, deploying, maintaining, and updating large scale systems in various sectors. A multi-faceted developer, knowledgeable in Java, SQL, React, Spring Boot, TensorFlow and Python. A true team player with experience working on development teams from South Africa, Zimbabwe, India and China. Analytical, motivated and hardworking with a strive for excellence displayed in hereunder results of past works. Seeking employment at a company involved with software development.

EDUCATION

B.sc (Hons) Computer Systems Engineering

University of Sunderland 07/2015 - 07/2019 Sunderland, UK

EXPERIENCE

Full Stack Developer

Software Application and Information Solutions (SAiS) 12/2020 - 08/2021 Gaborone, Botswana

Made technologies on the various applications supported as a vendor for companies. This entails providing developer support at the application and API level.

- Acted as sole developer on a module that would allow customers to log tickets on incidents, questions, or compliments, allowing an admin on the client system to reach out and chat with them all on the website. Developed the website using React and Spring Boot. This greatly reduced load on customer care unit freeing up time for more unique issues.
- Slashed image load times, reducing it by compressing and lazy loading images. This drastically improved load times by up to 40%.
- Refined a manual process by creating MySQL events to handle multiple actions upon "insert" when registering a new user, allowing the system to set a timer that would change values if the customer failed to verify their account. This removed lag times of having to manually perform the operation from IT side removing dependency on IT to register users.
- Redesigned the entire frontend of the client's customer portal. Updated it to take advantage of F-shape reading research, which increased website customer retention by 10%. After deployment of changes, educated trainees using presentations and code examples to guide them through the design thought process as well as other frontend design standards.
- Perfected the client's API, adding features that would convert user - provided data files to then automatically post to various banks. This automated a previously time-consuming and manual task that took hours

SKILLS

Client-Side

HTML . CSS . JS . Angular . React . Redux .

TypeScript • jQuery • Bootstrap

Server-side

Python • Java • REST • Android • Git • TensorFlow • MySQL • SQL • Oracle 11g • Machine Learning • Spring Boot

Development & Operations

JUnit · Mocha · Scrum · Agile ·

Test Driven Development • GIT

PROJECTS

BURS MTax

01/2018 - 07/2018 Gaborone, Botswana https://play.google.com/store/apps/details? id=com.burs.mtax&ql=US

Mtax offers tax payers services, employment Income Filing for Individuals, user Registration, remind Password, remind username, and change Password.

- · Using Android Studio (Java), screens and REST API were consumed using Retrofit
- · Backend was developed with Spring Boot
- · Database was developed using Oracle SQL
- Git version control was used to maintain testing and environments of the app and the webservices

STRENGTHS

Team Leadership

Analytical Skills

Innovative Thinking

Diagnostic & Troubleshooting Aptitude

Communication

EXPERIENCE

ATM & Cards Support Officer

African Banking Cooperation (BancABC) 05/2020 12/2020 Gaborone, Botswana

Supported all Botswana ATMs and cards issues. Using SQL and Linux to problem solve card declines, system failure and other various issues.

- Designed a database query to allow users to directly pull reports on ATM transactions by date. It was installed on a server and enabled users to download the data from the web page. This would extract transactional data from the database and distribute it via BI Publisher. This helped to mitigate any issues caused by IT staff running the report continuously in order to automate it for bank users also allowing searching of older data.
- Mitigated the reconciliation risk of missing ATM activity upon application crashes by developing a Python app to search ATM log files and return eJournal logs (the ATM activity during transactions and daily service) in a readable txt format. The old method was not always accurate, resulting in corrupted or missing eJournal entries.
- Deployed 4 deposit taking NCR ATMs to production and configured them onto the BankWorld system. This enabled the bank's service centers (which serve a small to medium population base) to accept deposits and cash withdrawals where they previously could not. As a result, all branches do not need to take in customers for deposit scenarios reducing bank teller congestion.
- Was part of a team that increased the bank's PCI compliance from 30% to nearly 70%. The goal of this project was to adhere to the PCI-DSS protocols and convert systems to be compliant. This project assisted in mitigating major risks such as hacking and policy failures.

Information Technology Officer

African Banking Cooperation (BancABC) 11/2019 - 05/2020 Gaborone, Botswana

Daily responsibilities were to manage staff calls as IT help desk, manage changes, handle major incident handling, and delegate tasks to other IT officers in different division. Another responsibilities included generating and formatting reports in Microsoft Excel and reporting to IT staff at the end of each month to discuss incident trends.

- Maximized work efficiency by developing a Python executable file
 that generates weekly and monthly reports in Microsoft Excel with
 graphs. This eliminated almost two hours spent from the old manual
 system for creating weekly reports and two weeks from the monthly
 reports. This sped up the process, allowing it to be completed in 10
 minutes with minor alterations to colors.
- Configured Microsoft Azure and Oracle Management Cloud to allow IT to monitor, alert and track web apps and servers. This helped to reduce response times to majority of critical severity incidents, to 10 min rather than the previous unmonitored which would at times take an hour or 2.

Intern Full Stack Developer

Botswana Unified Revenue Services (BURS) 01/2018 - 07/2018 Gaborone, Botswana

Daily responsibilities were to manage and assist on user complaints and compile reports in either Oracle database or Jaspersoft on request.

- Developed BURS' first Android application with Android Studio (Java with Retrofit) and Spring Boot frameworks. This application allowed users to file tax returns and pay off any outstanding tax debts. This project significantly reduced website traffic by funneling individual users to the application while the companies used the website, resulting in fewer server holdups and crashes per month (due to traffic) from 5 or 4 to 1.
- The mobile app has over 5000 installs, with all positive user feedback and few to no crashes.

